A big brother should always stay ahead of his little brother.
なんばむった
(南波六太)＜兄とは常に弟の先を
行かねばならない｡➡
ひびと
しかし 弟 日々人が栄光の
宇宙飛行士になった頃➡
However,
while my younger brother, Hibito, became an astronaut,
ひげき
兄の私 六太は 悲劇の無職に…＞
his older brother, Mutta, was tragically unemployed.
＜そんな中 思い出した
幼い日の約束＞
That's when I recalled the promise we made when we were kids.
⦅俺らは２人で
宇宙飛行士になるぞ⦆
(南波日々人)⦅うん！⦆
The two of us are gonna become astronauts.
Yep.
＜今の私には大きすぎる夢と
あきらめかけた時➡
Just as I was about ready to give up on my dream,
ある便りが私に届く＞
I received a special letter.
Your application has been accepted.
Yeah, I...
＜ああ 私は…私は…！➡
Your application has been accepted.
I...
あひゃあ！＞
＜宇宙へ行きたい！＞
want to go to space!
I will rise,
climb,
and shoot through the atmosphere
My goal is zero gravity
Space Brothers
Waves of people flood the intersection
Like vague silhouettes they stream past incessantly
How do I look in their midst?
I don't know
Hiding my true intentions desperately
I dish out vague excuses
My ambitions of going to space, harbored for so long,
are frail and brittle
No matter how I turn the globus
I have no home where I end up
There's no point to looking on a map
I will rise,
climb,
and shoot through the atmosphere
until I can look down on the entire world
I will yell
and scream
with a heart of steel
that I am going to zero gravity
#19 The Day Before Goodbye
ホァチオォー！アチョオー！
《泣けるぜ｡➡
I want to cry.
しかし この指令の実行も
残すところあと２日》
But I only have to follow this order for two more days.
Which means that we five will only be living in this sealed box for five more days...
《ということは 私達５人の
へいさ
閉鎖ボックスでの生活も➡
あと２日で…》
《終わろうとしていた》
The end is near.
《今日 寝たら
明日の朝 起きて…》
After going to sleep tonight and waking up tomorrow morning,
we'll have to select two people by the end of the day.
《その日のうちに ２人を選ぶ》
《そしたら この閉鎖ボックスとは
おさらばで➡
And then,
I say goodbye to this sealed box
みんなともお別れだ》
and to everyone else.
(ケンジ)≪なるほど≫
I see.
(ケンジ)面白いなぁ｡
(北村)すご～い｡上手だね｡
This is fascinating.
Wow, you're good.
(手島)なんか 照れるなぁ｡
You're embarrassing me.
I like the scientific approach of drawing organisms, based on
(ｹﾝｼﾞ)ちゃんと その星の
かんきょう
すいそく
環境データから推測して➡
生物をデザインしてるってのが
科学的でいいよね｡
specific planetary environment.
まあ ＮＡＳＡのｴｲﾑｽﾞ研究ｾﾝﾀｰの
真似っ子だよ 俺のは｡➡
Well, I'm just imitating work being done at the Ames Research Center.
Europa's Ocean
でも 昔からこういうの
好きなんだ｡➡
But I've always really enjoyed this.
たとえば 木星サイズの
わくせい
地球型惑星がどっかにあってさ…｡
For example, imagine a planet the size of Jupiter...
That means a diameter eleven times that of the Earth.
直径は地球の１１倍｡
(手島)海とかも 超でけ～の｡
The ocean would be enormous.
The organisms would be larger due to the planet's gravity and size.
星の重力やサイズに比例して
生物もみんなビッグ｡
There could be fish that dwarf the great blue whale.
そこには ｼﾛﾅｶﾞｽｸｼﾞﾗより はるかに
でかい魚がいるかも知れない｡
なんてね｡
Just dreaming.
(手島)子供の頃
そんなことばっか考えてた｡
I did a lot of dreaming as a kid.
I've done the same thing.
僕も まったく
同じこと考えたことあるよ｡
本当に!?
Really?
Sure.
なんか ゾクゾクするよね｡
It sends a shiver down your spine, right?
How about you, Kitamura?
(ケンジ)じゃあ 北村さんは？
えっ 私？…う～ん｡➡
Huh? Me?
自分のことで紹介できるものって
なかなかないなぁ｡じゃあ…➡
I don't have much to say about myself.
Well...
今読んでるＳＦ小説など…｡
Right now, I'm reading this science fiction novel.
あ いいね｡
Oh, that's a good one.
I realize they can get ridiculous, but I'm still a fan of space operas.
こうとうむけい
(北村)荒唐無稽とは
思うんだけど➡
やっぱりスペオペが好きなんだ｡
《これでよかったんだ 最初から》
This is how it should have been from the start.
(手島)これ 新作なの？
(北村)ううん｡閉鎖試験中に
もう一度読もうと思って｡
Is this a new release?
No, I just wanted to reread it during the exam.
(ケンジ)《終わる前に
気づけてよかった》
I'm glad we made this discovery before the end.
(原田)急にＢ班にも
笑顔が増えてきましたね｡
Team B has suddenly begun smiling a lot more.
Is that because we had Kitamura erase the data containing their scores?
北村さんに点数データを
削除してもらったからすかね｡
Yeah, that helped.
(星加)ああ それもあるけど➡
まかべ
真壁君が うまくきっかけを
作ってくれたよ｡
But Makabe was the catalyst.
これが 見たかった｡
This is what I wanted to see.
みぞぐち
真壁君と溝口君｡➡
Makabe or Mizoguchi...
どっちがリーダーとして
この班の雰囲気を作り出すか➡
Which would become the leader and set the team's tone?
I've been waiting for the answer.
それを待ってたんだ｡➡
２人には あえてｸﾞﾘｰﾝｶｰﾄﾞを
出さずにね｡
That was why I didn't give either one a green card.
Because this way, it would be more difficult for them.
(星加)この２人には カードを
出さないことの方が➡
しれん
試練だろうと思ってね｡➡
Am I a sadist?
エス
俺って Ｓかな？
Not at all...
ちょっと思いましたけど｡
Though I've had my doubts.
リーダーは 仕切ることだけが
仕事じゃないからな｡
A leader must do more than lead.
(星加)さあ もういいだろう｡
種明かしをしてやろう｡
Well, that's enough.
Time to show my hand.
２人にとっては➡
These green cards
救いのグリーンカードだ｡
will be their salvation.
《そういうことだったのか…》
So that's what was going on...
ホァチョオー！アチョー！
ホォーホォーホォー➡
(古谷)他にレパートリー
ないんか？
Don't you know any other tricks?
T-Tricks?
ホワ…レ レパ…｡
(新田)ブルース･リーにしちゃ➡
You need more muscle to do Bruce Lee, big brother.
筋肉が足りねえんじゃねえか？
お兄ちゃん｡
Oh, what?
ウ…オ…エエッ!?
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ]ホァチョオオー！
なすだ
(茄子田)あ 何？
彼 まだやってんの？
He's still doing that?
(原田)最終日まで続けろって
指令ですから｡
The order specified to continue until the final day.
う～ん 救われない
グリーンカードだねぇ…ねぇ｡
That was a punishing green card, yes?
ええ～ ウッホン！
(古谷)あ～あ…｡
え～ みなさま お集まりを｡
もう集まっとるちゅうねん！
Gather around, everyone.
Everyone's already here.
ウホン ウッホン！
え～ 実はですね➡
Well, you see...
良いニュースと 悪いニュースと
びみょう
あと 微妙なニュースがあります｡
I have some good news, some bad news,
and some dicey news.
どれから聞きたい？
Which do you want first?
なんか うっすら
ムカつく言い回しやな｡
You're making yourself sound like an ass.
じゃあ 悪いニュースから頼むよ｡
Could you start with the bad news?
え～…悪いニュースですね｡
Ah, the bad news...
I have some good news, some bad news,
良いニュースと 悪いニュースと➡
あと 微妙なニュースがあります｡
and some dicey news.
どれから聞きたい？
Which do you want first?
なんか うっすら
ムカつく言い回しやな｡
You're making yourself sound like an ass.
じゃあ 悪いニュースから頼むよ｡
Could you start with the bad news?
え～…悪いニュースですね｡
Ah, the bad news...
前々から食料が
足りないということで➡
To compensate for the shortage,
だかいさく
打開策として 毎食
誰かひとりが食事を抜くという➡
we decided that one person would skip each meal.
方策でやってまいりましたが
どうやら私の計算ミスです｡
But apparently, my calculations were off.
思ったより減りが早く
明日の分がありません！
We've run out faster than anticipated, so we've nothing left for tomorrow.
(せりか)《ハッ!!》
《おかわりしすぎた…》
I shouldn't have had seconds!
It'll be fine if we don't eat for one day.
大丈夫だろ｡１日ぐらい｡
みんなでダイエットしようぜ｡
We'll all diet together.
じゃあ 良いニュースって何や？
So what's the good news?
フフン…良いニュースはこちら！
The good news is over here.
なんと 小麦粉を発見！
I discovered some flour!
There's also water and salt, along with seasonings.
あと 水と塩もあるし
その他 調味料もそろってる！
これで明日は
うどんが食えるぜ みんな！
We're having noodles tomorrow, guys!
ハアァ…！
Hold on... Wait a sec!
ちょ～ 待て 待て待て！
材料はあっても➡
We have the ingredients, but what if no one knows how to make noodles?
作り方がわからへん的な
オチかもしれんぞ｡➡
Do you know how to make noodles, Nanba?
うどんの作り方 ちゃんと
知ってんのやろな？南波！
もちのろんだよ！
You bet!
ただし バッチリ
仕込まなきゃならない｡
But there's a lot of prep work involved.
うどんは 一日にしてならず｡
They aren't made in a day...
Well, it'll only take two or three hours.
いや まあ
２～３時間で できるけど➡
But I'll need everyone's help.
みんなの協力が必要なのです｡
では まず…｡
So first—
Let's get started...
ほな 始めよか～｡
ハハハ…そうだね｡
Indeed.
ん!? 使わねぇか？掃除機｡
Don't we need a vacuum?
You want to clean before we've even started?
(古谷)作る前に かたす気か｡
Um, four percent salt water...
え～と ４％の塩水っていうと…｡
うん いいんじゃない？
Mm, this should be good.
よ～し ぴったり！
Yep, perfect.
粉と水が
よく馴染むように混ぜるんだ｡
Mix the flour and water well,
ダマが なくなるまでね｡
until there aren't any lumps.
Right.
This is my first time making noodles.
(新田)初めてだな
うどんを作るなんて｡
私もだよ｡
(古谷)そやけど
こんなに食べ切れるんか？
Same here.
Will we be able to finish all of this?
大丈夫です！あ いや…｡
That won't be a problem.
Um, er...
うどんって 結構ツルッて
いけちゃうんじゃないんですか？
Noodles aren't really all that filling...
男性の皆さんなら｡
ま それもそうやな｡
And we have all these big boys here.
Well, that's true.
南波君は うどんの作り方まで
よく知ってるね｡
I'm impressed that you know how to make this, Nanba.
前に シャロンおばちゃん
って人の所で➡
I've done it once before, at the observatory, with Aunt Sharon.
作った事があって｡天文台で…｡
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)という事で 六太 日々人｡
今日は うどんを作るわよ｡
Okay, Mutta? Hibito?
Today, we'll be making noodles.
(２人)作れるの!?
We can make noodles?
ええ！意外と簡単なのよ｡➡
Yes, it's easier than you realize.
小麦粉と塩と水｡➡
Flour, salt, and water...
That's all you need.
基本的には
これだけで できちゃうのよ｡
やってみる？
Want to try?
You bet!
ヤッタヤッター！
はか
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)まずは 粉を量って…｡
First, measure the flour.
クシュン！あっ…｡
アハハ ごめ～ん！
Sorry!
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)はい 混ぜて｡➡
Now mix it.
Stop.
ストップ!!➡
Now mix it.
はい 混ぜて｡
ダマにならないようにね｡
Make sure there aren't any lumps.
よ～く かき混ぜて｡
Mix it up well.
あ 色が…｡
ウフフ…｡➡
Oh, it's changing color.
黄色っぽくなると
ちょうどいいのよ｡
Once it turns yellow, it's ready.
で これをね…｡
Next, you take this...
And you use your feet to knead it.
足で踏んで こねま～す｡
なんか不思議…｡
This is so weird.
そして呪文を唱えます｡
And start chanting the spell.
おいしくな～れ おいしくな～れ｡
Yummy, yummy...
Yummy, yummy.
しばらく生地を寝かせたら
これの登場よ！➡
After kneading for a while, switch to these.
めんぼう
麺棒っていうの｡
They're called rolling pins.
Rolling pins?
メンボー？
Rolling pin!
メーン！ボー!!
やめろ このっ！
Quit it...
はいはい 遊ばない｡
All right. Stop fooling around.
いい？よく見てて｡➡
Listen up, and watch closely.
こうして…押して伸ばして➡
You press, press, and stretch...
そしたら コロコロコロ～ッて
平らにするのよ｡
Then you roll it all up, until it's flat.
さあ やってみて｡
Now give it a try.
Okay!
よ～し！
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)伸ばしたら たたみます｡
Once you've stretched it out, fold it up.
(田村)で 切っていきま～す｡
Then you chop it.
What? Tamura's doing the chopping?
田村のね～ちゃんが切んの？
あら あたし上手いのよ｡
Yes, I'm quite good.
Wow, you really are good.
うわ ホントだ スゲェ！
Cook the noodles for ten minutes, and then they're done.
１０分ゆでたら できあがりよ｡
Yummy noodles!
うどんちゃん！
しっかり ゆだれよ～｡
Cook away!
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)きつねとたぬきの
お月見うどん！召し上がれ｡
This is a combination of three different styles.
(一同)いただきま～す！
Let's eat!
ウフフ…｡
どう？おいしい？
Well? How is it?
(２人)おいし～い!!
It's great!
現在
自分で作ったうどんに
すっかり感動しちゃって➡
I enjoyed making noodles so much,
I was always eating them at the observatory.
天文台では うどんばっかり
食べてたなぁ｡なつかしいな…｡
Brings back memories...
あの…天文台って
どこのですって？
U-Um, which observatory are you talking about?
Huh?
え？ああ
シャロンおばちゃんのね｡
Oh, this was Aunt Sharon's observatory.
Huh?
What?!
シャロンって あの
カネコ･シャロン博士？
Do you mean Dr. Kaneko Sharon?
天文学者の!?
そ～だよ｡
The astronomer?!
Yeah.
本当に!?私 本持ってます！
Really?!
I own one of her books!
マジか ジブン!?
うん｡英語も教えてもらったよ｡
Are you serious?
Yeah.
She taught me English.
え～いいな～!!
うらやましい話だな｡
Wow! That's great...
You're making me jealous.
確か シャロンっていう名前の
小惑星があるんだよな｡
Isn't there an asteroid named Sharon?
そうです そうです！
Yeah...
That's right! That's right!
Her husband, Kaneko Shinichi, also an astronomer, discovered it and named it after his wife!
同じ天文学者で旦那さんの
金子進一博士が発見して➡
奥さんの名前をつけたんですよ！
ねっ 南波さん？
Isn't that right, Nanba?
ああ そうだよ｡
Yeah, that's right.
《すっげ～｡みんな
シャロンのこと知ってるんだ》
Wow...
Everyone knows Sharon...
《今まで こんなこと
一度もなかった…》
This hasn't ever happened before.
なに～？天文台!?
What?
The observatory?
そう！シャロンっていう
天文学者がいてさ➡
Yep, there's an astronomer named Sharon there...
スッゲー面白いよ｡みんなでさ…｡
She's a really fun person!
Let's go together.
あんな不気味なとこ
誰が行くかよ バーカ！
Why would we go to that creepy place, dummy?
だいたい 星なんて見て
何がうれし～んだよ｡➡
What's the point of looking at a bunch of stars?
良さが分からん｡
ただの光る点だし｡
I don't get it.
They're just shiny dots.
《て てん…!?》
D-Dots?
うわ～たたた…!!
現在
《あの頃から 私は
心のどこかで諦めていた》
After that,
I pretty much gave up.
《わかってくれる奴なんて
誰ひとりいないんだと…》
I figured that no one else would ever understand.
But they were right here.
《ここにいたんだ》
There were people who would've been eager to come along.
《誘ったら 喜んで
ついて来てくれそうな連中が》
《ここに…いたんだ…》
They've been here all this time.
＜私達は うどんを作りながら
いっぱい話した＞
We chatted about everything while we made the noodles.
＜サーベイヤー３号に
付着していた微生物の事とか➡
Like the bacteria found on Surveyor 3.
昔 話題になった
火星の人魚の事とか…＞
The statue on Mars that caused such a fuss.
クマムシって
火星でも生きていけるんだぜ｡
知ってるて！
Waterbears can live on Mars.
I knew that.
You're talking about tardigrades, right?
タルディスの実験やろ？
(福田)絶対零度でも
生き残れるもんね｡
They can survive at absolute zero.
We discussed some very hardcore topics.
＜結構 マニアックな話もした＞
That's crazy!
＜俺の話が通じてる！＞
They understand what I'm saying.
＜みんなの話も
手に取るようにわかる＞
And I know what everyone is talking about.
This was fun...
＜楽しい！
とにかく楽しかった！＞
It was so much fun.
That's right, Nanba.
そういえば 南波君｡
What was the dicey news you had?
もうひとつの微妙なニュースって
何だったの？
ん？まあ それは…➡
Hmm?
O-Oh, right...
ニュースっていうより
再確認で…➡
It's not really news, just a reminder.
I'm sure that everyone already knows this...
みんな わかってる事だと
思うけど…➡
明日 必ず この中から２人
選ばなきゃいけない…｡
Tomorrow, we have to choose two people.
And then I say goodbye to this sealed box.
《そしたら この閉鎖ボックスとは
おさらばで…➡
And to everyone else...
みんなとも お別れなんだ…》
The lens inside my eyes
went completely out of focus when I saw you
The signs of love flooded the occipital lobe of my cerebrum
The words the left side of my brain produced
brought my vocal cords to reverberation
Vigorously my confession traversed my tongue
May I love you?
May I really love you?
May I be beside you? (The concentration of my hormones rose)
(Dopamine overwhelmed me)
Can I hold your hand? (My blood circulation powered up)
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#20 The Worst Possible
Punishment
＜ついに 閉鎖環境最終日
私達は➡
We're on our last day in the sealed box.
We must decide who would make the best astronaut.
宇宙飛行士に ふさわしい者を
自分達で選ぶことに＞
ジャクサ
＜ＪＡＸＡが見たいのは➡
JAXA wants to see if we're ready to make necessary sacrifices.
誰かを切り捨てる非情さを
持てるかどうかだけど…＞
＜あなたのことなら
あなたの胸が知ってるもんよ＞
I'm sure you know what's right in your heart.
＜そうか…｡
みんな！この方法で決めよう＞
I know...
Everyone, let's use this method to decide!
(古谷)＜はぁ!?
そんなん ありえへん＞
What? That's crazy!
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"The Worst Possible Punishment"
＜誰が一番強いか
答えを知っている奴いるか？＞
Does anyone know the strongest candidate?
パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
カッコイイ！
Cool stuff!